kara no kokoro wo terasu mono wa nani?
What brightens up an empty heart?
sakebi tsuzukeru hikari todoku made
I will keep on singing until the light reaches you
falling through the cracks kurayami e ochiteku
Falling through the cracks, Falling into the darkness
anata no sono te o zettai hanasanai
I will never let go of your hand
tell me the story of your life mada michi no tochuu
Tell me the story of your life, We're still on our way
anata o watashi wa zettai akiramenai
I will never give up on you
osaerarenai shoudou nanigenai hibi wa aijyou
Urges I can't suppress, I live for the ordinary days
natsukashii kaze ni furimukeba itsud
When I turn my cheek to a nostalgic wind
emo anata no koe ga suru yo
I always hear your voice
underdog wa wander around
Underdog will Wander around
mawari michi shitemo nigeru yori mashi yo
Even if I take the long way around,
it's better than running away
jibun de jibun o shinjirare nakucha dare wo shinjiru no?
If I can't learn to believe in myself,
then who can I believe in?
hikari ni sono te kazase
Hold up your hand to the light
shining through the clouds kurayami e ochiteku
Shining through the clouds, Falling into the darkness
anata no sono te o zettai hanasanai
I will never let go of your hand
tell me what is on your mind hateshinai yume wo
Tell me what is on your mind,
Chasing the never ending dream
oikake bokura wa zettai akiramenai
We will never give up
kotae no nai jinsei ni kujike sou ni naru kedo
Discouraged by a life without answers, but I...
don’t give it up! keep it up! turn it upside down!
Don't give it up! Keep it up! Turn it upside down!
kokoro wa tsunagatteru yo tatoe tooku hanaretemo
Our hearts will always be connected,
no matter how far apart we may be
tomo ni tomo ni ikiteyukou
Let's share this life together
Naruto Shippuden,
Sasuke's Story:
Sunrise,
Part 2: Coliseum
"Encountered Exploding Humans."
(カカシ)「起爆人間に遭遇。
"Will investigate independently.
Please approve."
独自に調査を行う
了承されたし」か。
Just how long will
your journey continue?
(カカシ)
お前の旅は いつまで続くんだ。
Sasuke, where are you going?
(チノ)サスケちゃん
どこに行くの？
You're Sasuke Uchiha, right?
(ノワキ)キミだよね
うちはサスケ。
The lone survivor of
the exalted Uchiha Clan.
(チノ)誇り高き
うちは一族唯一の生き残り。
I knew it the moment I saw
your Sharingan last night.
(ノワキ)ゆうべの写輪眼を見て
すぐにわかったよ。
Where are you going now?
That has nothing to do with you.
これから どこ行くの？
It does involve us!
(サスケ)お前たちには関係ない。
関係なくないよ！
Amino...
... made us yummy meals.
アミノさんは
おいしいご飯作ってくれたよ。
She was kind.
優しかったよ。
You're going to look for
that Fuushin guy, right?
風心ってやつ
捜すんだよね？
But isn't he the one who changed
Amino and the others
えっ え～
そいつでしょ？
into the human something
or other, right?
アミノさんたちを
なんとか人間にしちゃったの！
We're going with you.
I think we may be able to help.
私らも ついてくよ。
何かの役に立てると思う。
うん。
And don't give us that look that says
"I don't need you guys!"
(チノ)そんなふうに お前らなんか
必要ないって態度とられると→
That will only make us more determined!
Sasuke dear, are you listening?!
反抗したくなるんだけど！
ねぇ サスケちゃんってば！
あれ？
I don't care what you do.
Just stop calling me that.
どうでもいいが
その呼び方はやめろ。
I figure I'm older than you,
Sasuke dear.
私は サスケちゃんより
年上だと思うよ。
So I can call you "dear."
だから
ちゃんづけでもいいじゃん。
Older? You?
年上？ お前が？
エッヘン！
Ahem!
By that much?
What do you mean by "that much"?
そんなにか。
何が そんなになのかな？
Sasuke dear, it's not good
to judge people by their looks
サスケちゃんさ
見た目や思い込みで→
or by your impression of them.
人を判断しないほうが
いいと思うよ。
You shouldn't judge people
by their looks or
by your impression of them.
((イタチ : 見た目や思い込みだけで→
HIDDEN LEAF POLICE FORCE
Are you going to join too, Big Brother?
人を判断しないほうがいいですよ。
I wonder...
兄さんも ここに入るの？
You should! When I'm older...
(イタチ)さあ どうかなあ？
I'm going to join
the Leaf Police Force too!
そうしなよ
大きくなったら→
Forgive me, Sasuke...
俺も警務部隊に
入るからさ！
This is the last time.
許せ サスケ
これで最後だ。
No matter what happens from now,
I will love you always.
お前が これからどうなろうと→
(俺は お前を
ずっと愛している))
Sasuke dear!
(チノ)…ちゃん サスケちゃん！
By the way... Have you been back to
the Hidden Leaf Village, Sasuke dear?
そういえばさ サスケちゃんは
木ノ葉隠れの里に帰ってんの？
What? Ignoring me again?
What about reviving the Uchiha Clan?
You're the lone survivor, right?
アッハ また無視かい。
うちはの復興とか
あるんじゃないの？
Hello! Are you there, Sasuke?!
生き残り１人なんでしょ？
もしも～し
聞こえてますか～？
Chino, stop it.
Whose side are you on anyway?
You know, you...
チノ やめとけ。
あんたは どっちの味方なのよ
だいたい ノワキはね…。
Hey, where are we going?
ところでさ
どこに向かってんの？
Ignoring me again!
また無視かい。
ん。
I mean...
Hey.
だって～！
おい。
My name isn't "hey"!
私の名前は
おいじゃないんですけどぉ？
You asked if I'm going to
look for Fuushin.
The answer is yes.
風心を捜すのかと聞いたな？
そのとおりだ。
Huh?
That's what I should do right now.
え？
それが 今
俺のやるべきことだ。
A-Any ideas on where to look?
アテはあるんだよね？
The only thing that can create
an Exploding Human
起爆人間を生み出せるのは
血継限界くらいのものだ。
is a Kekkei Genkai.
H-Hey, Sasuke dear...
Hold on a minute...
あっ あ～
ちょっと サスケちゃん待ってよ！
You think you'll find him inside
that really scary-looking cave?
(チノ)で あの
いかにも怪しげな洞窟の中に→
そのアテがいるの？
Ignoring me again!
また無視 …ん。
You're Sasuke, right?
(ヤマト)サスケ だね？
You can call me Yamato.
(ヤマト)僕は ヤマトと
名乗っておこうか。
Since you're watching over this place,
it must mean that Orochimaru is here.
監視がいるということは
大蛇丸は ここにいるんだな？
O-Orochimaru? You mean that—?!
What's the purpose of your visit?
お 大蛇丸って あの!?
I can't allow just anyone through
to see Orochimaru.
用件を聞かせてくれるかい？
大蛇丸に
接触しようとする人間を→
Regarding the Exploding Humans
that attacked the Hidden Leaf...
素通りさせる訳には
いかないんでね。
木ノ葉で起きた
起爆人間の襲撃。
It's possible Orochimaru may have
information about the perpetrator.
その首謀者に
つながる情報を→
大蛇丸が
持っている可能性がある。
Did you send word about this
to Lord Sixth?
I intend to, if I get results.
６代目には この件
連絡したの？
結果が出れば
報告するつもりだ。
It would be much easier for us
to coordinate things,
う～ん 逐一 途中経過を
送ってもらったほうが→
if you'd send us progress reports...
こっちとしても
連携とりやすいんだけどな。
However...
でも…。
You're doing this all for the sake
for the Hidden Leaf, right?
木ノ葉のために
動いてるんだよね？
Yeah...
ああ。
Then there's nothing else to say.
はあ 仕方がないな。
I'll send Lord Sixth a report.
６代目には
僕から報告しておくよ。
Remember, we're comrades.
I'm sure Mr Kakashi also taught you
the importance of trust and teamwork.
仲間だからね。
信頼と チームワークの大切さは→
キミも カカシさんに
教わっただろう？
Thank you...
すまない。
It's been a long time, Sasuke.
(大蛇丸)久しぶりね サスケ君。
You've brought some
interesting-looking friends with you.
おもしろそうな友達
連れてるじゃない。
Do you know Fuushin
of the Lightning Gang?
雷光団の風心を知っているか？
What? Not even a greeting?
You're as blunt as ever.
あら 挨拶もなし？
Tell me everything you know.
相変わらず唐突ね。
知っていることがあるなら
すべて話せ。
Is that any way to ask
a person something?
それが
人に ものを頼む態度かしら？
Hurry up.
さっさとしろ。
Fuushin possesses a Kekkei Genkai...
風心は血継限界の持ち主で→
I believe he originally was a member
of En Oyashiro's guard unit.
もとは
御屋城エンの護衛団にいたはずよ。
En Oyashiro?
He's not affiliated with any group.
御屋城エン？
どこにも属さない男でね→
Even though he's a shinobi,
he's an arms trader.
忍でありながら
武器商人でもある男よ。
He'll sell weapons to anyone
for the right price,
カネさえ積めば 誰にでも
武器を売りさばくもんだから→
so he's known as
the "Merchant of Death."
He's amassed a huge fortune
during his lifetime.
死の商人なんて呼ばれていたわ。
一代で莫大な財を築いた
やり手ね。
Where is he?
Who knows...
どこにいる？
さあ。
He has a hideout
even better hidden than mine.
彼は私以上に
アジトを持っているようだから。
I think finding him
will be very difficult.
捜すとなると
難しいかもしれないわね。
For you, even the difficult is easy.
その難しいことも
あんたなら簡単にできるはずだ。
Does that mean you trust me?
ククク… 信頼されているのかしら？
Well, I don't know where to find him,
but I can lure him out.
そうね
どこにいるかはわからないけど→
おびき寄せることはできるわ。
However...
that may cause a few problems.
でも それには 面倒なことが
あるかもしれないわよ？
Why do you think I came here?
何のために
ここまで来たと思っている。
How unlike you...
らしくないわね。
I'm just doing what I have to.
やるべきことを やるだけだ。
I sense the wind.
クク… 風を感じるわ。
Wait here.
It will take some time to prepare.
ちょっと待ってて
準備に時間がかかるから。
Sasuke dear!
I didn't know that
you knew Orochimaru.
サスケちゃん！
I don't recall ever telling you.
大蛇丸と知り合いだなんて
聞いてないよ。
言った覚えもない。
むぅ…。
Sasuke!
Hey! Why didn't you
let me know you're coming?
(香燐)サスケ！ アハッ なんだよ～。
来るなら来るって… ん？
Sasuke dear...
"Sasuke dear"?!
サスケちゃん…。
サスケ… ちゃん？
What? Is she your girlfriend, Sasuke?
(水月)ん？ なに？
その子 サスケの彼女？
You mean, that ugly hag?
こ こんな へちゃむくれが→
Hey! Who're you calling ugly?!
か… かか… 彼女とか
ありえねえだろうが！
Sasuke, say it's not true!
ちょっと！
へちゃむくれって誰のこと!?
It's not true.
サスケ 嘘だと言ってくれよ。
嘘だ。
ほ～。
You should've seen
the look of panic on your face.
フン どうだろうね 今の慌てっぷり。
Shut up!
If it weren't for that
big mouth of yours!
黙れ！ お前がくだんねえこと
言うからじゃねえか。
That's no excuse for looking like...
- It's been awhile.
- it's the end of the world!
(水月)だからって
世界の終わりみたいな…。
You've been continuing your travels?
(重吾)久しぶりだな。
うん。
ずっと旅を続けているのか？
Yeah.
You haven't gone back to
Hidden Leaf Village?
あぁ。
See, you're worried sick
about Sasuke.
木ノ葉には帰ってねえの？
やっぱ サスケのことが
気になってしようがないんじゃん。
You're really getting on my nerves!
マジで うっせえな てめえは！
Quiet, you guys.
あんたたち うるさいわよ。
I'm ready. Shall we go?
準備が整ったわ。
行きましょうか。
Lord Orochimaru, are you going out?
大蛇丸様
どこか出かけるんですか？
Sasuke and I are going to the sea.
サスケ君と ちょっと海にね。
Huh?!
The ocean? With Sasuke?
えっ えぇ～っ！ サスケと海に…。
You all will stay and mind the fort.
The sea with Lord Orochimaru?
I can't quite picture it.
(大蛇丸)あなたたちは留守番よ。
大蛇丸様と海って
なんか想像つかないっすね。
Wait, that's news to me too.
To be more precise,
a solitary island in the sea.
待て 俺も初耳だ。
正確に言えば 海に浮かぶ孤島よ。
There's a paradise for the wealthy there.
その島に金持ちの娯楽場があるの。
And that's where En Oyashiro is?
If he takes the bait.
そこに御屋城がいるのか？
エサに食いつけば… ね。
- Nowaki.
- Yeah.
Sasuke...
ノワキ。
ああ。
サスケ～。
Bleh!
ベーッ！
What's with that girl?
Wanna fight?
あ？
Oh, what a drag.
なんだ あのアマ やんのか こら！
あ～ もう 面倒くさいな。
Sasuke working for
the sake of strangers...
(水月)
サスケが他人のために動くとはね。
The Hidden Leaf was attacked...
They're not strangers...
襲われたのは木ノ葉の里なんだ。
But he didn't return to the village.
他人というわけでもないだろう。
I wonder if it's hard
for him to go back?
でもさ 木ノ葉には
帰ってないんでしょ。
Don't you guys get it?
やっぱ いづらいのかな？
The big war might be over,
(香燐)わかってねえな。
but there are still lots of
dangerous characters lurking around.
でかい戦争がなくなったって
やばいヤローはいくらでもいんだろ。
As long as Sasuke has those eyes...
shinobi will continue
to attack the village.
サスケがあの目を持っている以上→
So by showing that Sasuke Uchiha
isn't in Hidden Leaf Village
里を襲う忍も出てくるだろ。
だから うちはサスケは
木ノ葉にはおらず→
and he's still journeying
around the world,
常に世界を放浪してるって
まわりに示すことで→
it lessens the possibility that
the village will be harmed.
里に被害が及ぶ可能性も
減るってわけ。
So then,
Sasuke has to continue traveling?
それなら サスケは
ずっと旅を続けんの？
That might be it.
(重吾)そうなるのかもしれないな。
Still...
The fact that you, the one who instigated
the destruction of the Hidden Leaf,
しかし 木ノ葉崩しに
四代目風影暗殺…。
the assassination of the Fourth Kazekage
and countless other horrific crimes,
can still move around freely
is quite astonishing.
他にも さまざまな大罪を
犯してきたあんたが→
こうやって自由に動けるってのも
奇妙な話だな。
I'm not free.
(大蛇丸)ククッ…。
And who are you to talk, Sasuke?
自由ではないわよ。
By all rights, you should be locked up.
それに サスケ君がそれを言う？
あなただって本来なら
投獄されてた身の上でしょ。
But even Kabuto,
one of the war criminals from
the Fourth Ninja World War
まあ 第四次忍界大戦の
戦犯の一人 カブトだって今や→
is now the director of an orphanage...
Kabuto is?
孤児院の院長なんだけどね。
Of course, compared to me,
カブトが…。
もっとも私に比べれば→
the likelihood that Kabuto will
resort to evil is lower.
カブトのほうが 悪に走る確率は
低いでしょうけど。
How can you be so sure?
Don't you trust the power
of Itachi Uchiha?
なぜ そう言い切れる？
フフッ うちはイタチの力を
信用できないの？
You and I, and Kabuto
could just be insurance...
in case something happens that cannot
be countered with common sense.
(大蛇丸)私もあなたも
そしてカブトも→
常識で対処できないことが
起きたときのための→
Insurance?
In every era, a maverick appears.
保険かもしれないわね。
保険？
When that happens, there may be
a need for people like us
どの時代も異端児は現れるもの。
who possess powers
considered to be inhuman.
そのとき 私たちのような→
There are things that cannot be
protected by righteousness alone.
非人道的な力が必要な場合もある。
If that's the case, keeping us around
like pets might be mutually beneficial.
正しさだけでは
守れないものもあるんだから。
だったら
うまく飼いならしたほうが→
But...
お互いのためになることも…。
your friend would never even
think of such a tactic.
でも まあ あなたのお友達は→
そんな駆け引き
一切 頭にないでしょうけどね。
Probably not.
There...
You can see it in the distance.
そうだろうな。
(大蛇丸)さて 見えてきたわね。
Where are we?
This is an island that
you can't find on any map.
ここ どこ？
Oh...
ここは地図にも載らない孤島よ。
Let's go.
はぁ…。
さあ 行きましょ。
What is this place?
It's called the Coliseum.
なんなの ここ？
Coliseum?
コロシアムと呼ばれてるわ。
コロシアム？
Is everyone enjoying themselves so far?
ご来場の皆々様 楽しんで
いただいてますでしょうか？
Honors to the victor!
Despair to the vanquished!
As you know, the rules are simple!
[マイク]勝者に栄光 敗者に絶望！
The one with your ID tag goes up against
one with another person's ID tag.
ルールはご存じ 自分の手札と
相手の手札を戦わせるだけ！
And the winner is whoever manages
to take his opponent's ID tag...
Simply put, it's a survival match!
そして 勝ったほうが どちらも
手に入れることができる→
弱肉強食シンプルスタイルと
なっております！
What's going on, Orochimaru?
You heard the explanation.
どういうことだ 大蛇丸。
The wealthy patrons here pit their shinobi
against shinobi employed by others.
あの説明どおり
ここにいる金持ち連中は→
The losing shinobi becomes theirs.
お抱えの忍を戦わせて→
勝ったら相手の忍を
手に入れることができるのよ。
And now, today's semi-final match!
Now entering the ring...
それでは 本日のセミファイナル！
Wearing the ID tag of President Makibi
of the Makibi Corporation...
[マイク]まず入場してきたのは
マキビコーポレーション社長→
Raimei, the Black Lightning Flash!
マキビ様の手札 黒い稲光 ライメイ！
His opponent...
Wearing the ID tag of President Himeyuri
of the Himeyuri Company...
[マイク]対するは ヒメユリカンパニー頭取
ヒメユリ様の手札→
Suzuran, the Eerie Flame
of the White Moon!
月白の妖炎 スズラン！
This place is like a casino.
(大蛇丸)この場は 一種のカジノなの。
All right, let's begin!
It's now or never, no foul play,
no grudges afterwards...
それでは まいりましょう！
A single-bout challenge!
待ったなし 反則なし
恨みっこなしの一本勝負！
Ready?
Fight!
レディ！
(観客たち)ファイト！
I don't have time to waste
on sick hobbies.
Where is En Oyashiro?
趣味の悪い道楽に
つきあっている暇はない。
I wonder...
But this is about the only place
that he'll show up.
御屋城エンは どこだ？
(大蛇丸)さぁ？
でも 御屋城エンは→
Although, he won't come
if there's no shinobi he wants.
ここくらいにしか
姿を見せないのよ。
しかも
欲しい手札がなければ 現れない。
Whoa! Suzuran is down!
The winner is Raimei!
おっと！ スズラン ダウン!!
President Makibi is overjoyed!
勝利したのは ライメイ！
You're useless!
[マイク]マキビ社長も大喜び！
Why do you think
I kept you all this time?!
(ヒメユリ)この役立たずが！
You ingrate...
(ヒメユリ)何のために これまで
飼ってきたと思ってるざます！
This place is worthless.
この恩知らずめが！
Then why don't you help?
ろくでもない場所だな。
To a victim, the assailant and
a third party are no different.
(チノ)だったら 助けてあげれば？
被害者にしてみれば
加害者も第三者も一緒。
People are no better than the assailant
if they didn't try to help.
自分を救ってくれなかった人たち
それで ひとくくり。
If you only pity the loser and do nothing
to stop the decadence of the rich...
ここで行われている金持ちどもの
道楽を止めることなく→
you're just as guilty, Sasuke.
同情的な言葉を
口にするだけのサスケちゃんだって→
Chino, stop.
共犯者にすぎないよ。
(ノワキ)チノ よせ。
Chino!
Was this sight too shocking
for a child?
チノ！
No, she's older than me.
子供に見せるには
刺激が強すぎたかしら？
What?
いや 俺より年上だ。
The wait is finally over!
Now, for the main event!
え…。
Wearing En Oyashiro's ID tag is Futsu!
[マイク]お待たせしました。
本日のメインイベント！
[マイク]まず 現れたのは
御屋城エン様の手札 フツ！
It seems he took the bait.
And his opponent will be wearing
Lord Orochimaru's ID tag...
エサに食いついてくれたようね。
The legendary shinobi who attacked
the Five Kage Conference...
相対しますは 大蛇丸様の手札！
The last Uchiha...
Sasuke Uchiha!
あの五影会談を襲撃した
伝説の男！
最後のうちは うちはサスケだ！
What is the meaning of this?!
I told you. Oyashiro will only
appear for something he wants.
どういうことだ？
言ったでしょ？ 御屋城は
欲しい手札がないと現れないって。
He is... a collector of Kekkei Genkai.
A collector of Kekkei Genkai?
彼ね 血継限界コレクターなの。
Yes...
As for you with
your Sharingan, Sasuke...
血継限界コレクター？
そう。
He probably wants you so bad,
he can taste it.
写輪眼を持つサスケ君なら→
Couldn't he have just searched
for me if he knew I was here?
喉から手が出るほどに
欲しいでしょうね。
Oyashiro is a careful man.
会場内にいるとわかれば
捜せばいいだけじゃないのか。
He can easily camouflage his scent,
let alone his appearance and form.
(大蛇丸)御屋城は用心深い男で→
Who knows where he is?
姿かたちは もちろん
においを消すのも難なくこなす。
However, he will definitely appear
after the match for the ID tag transfer.
どこにいるかはわからないわ。
ただ 試合終了の手札譲渡の場に
必ず出てくる。
That's the custom here.
Wait a minute,
could this be a default?
それが ここのしきたりなの。
チッ…。
Now go...
おっと！ 棄権ですか？
He's here! He arrives, ready to go!
さぁ。
Sasuke Uchiha has appeared!
[マイク]来た～！ 満を持して登場
うちはサスケのお出ましだ!!
So that's Sasuke Uchiha.
Let me see your Sharingan.
(エン)あれが うちはサスケ…。
All right, let us begin!
見せてよね 写輪眼。
It's now or never, no foul play,
no grudges afterwards...
それでは まいりましょう！
A single-bout challenge!
待ったなし 反則なし
恨みっこなしの一本勝負！
Ready...
Fight!
レディ！
(観客たち)ファイト！
Vapor Style: Solid Fog Jutsu, eh?
沸遁 巧霧の術だな。
P-President Makibi?
Is he all right?!
A-Ambulance!
Call an ambulance!
マ… マキビ社長！
[マイク]救護班… 救護班 呼んで！
An Exploding Human?
sayonara arigatou
Good bye, thank you
《起爆人間？》
koko kara habatakou
We're flying away from here
karappo no tenohira nigirishimete sa
Our empty hands squeezed tight
namida ja nagasenai tashika na omoi ga atta
Not even tears could wash away these feelings
kagiri aru sekai e fumidasu yo
We're stepping out into a world with limits
ashita moshi bokura ga koko kara kietemo
Even if we're suddenly gone tomorrow
kawari nante hoka ni mo irundesho?
There would be others who could replace us, right?
jishin nante hajime kara motte wa inai kedo
We were never confident to begin with
akiramerarenainda
But we can't seem to give it up
isso
What if...
zenbu o suteraretara
We just abandon everything and call it quits?
motto raku ni naru ka na
Would things be easier?
sonna imeeji hitotsu de
That image alone
matataku ma ni toozakatteyuku mirai
was enough to grab on hold to the future
dakishimeta
that was quickly fading away
sayonara arigatou
Good bye, thank you
muchuu de habatakou
We're flying away with everything we got
kagiri aru sekai no sono naka ni
Into a world with limits
sayonara arigatou sayonara arigatou
Good bye, thank you
kanarazu mata aeru sono basho de
We'll definitely meet again, back there
The Chinoike Clan?
Seems the Uchiha Clan who
suffered long through persecution
were also complicit in
the persecution of others...
Did Itachi know about this?
You might find something
if you go to Hell Valley.
I want to see this Hell Valley
with my own eyes...
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"Sasuke's Story: Sunrise, Part 3:
Fuushin"
As the only survivor of
the Uchiha Clan, I'll...